Register of the Boris Nikolaevich Kompaneiskii Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Boris Nikolaevich Kompaneiskii papers,
1921-1973
2001C15
Kompaneiskii, Boris Nikolaevich, 1885-1965
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings and miscellany, relating to physiology, Russian literature, and Russian émigré affairs. Microfilm.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biographical Note
1885 November 18 Born, St. Petersburg, Russia
1908 Degree in physiology, St. Peterburg University, Russia
1924 Degree, psycho-physiology, Moscow State University, Soviet Union
1926-1941 Worked as a researcher and professor in various laboratories and institutes, including the Moscow Academy of Arts, the Herzen Pedagogical Institute and Institute for Brain Research, Leningrad, Soviet Union
1942 Arrives in Berlin, Germany
1943-1946 Researcher and laboratory director, Physiological Institute, University of Vienna, and Psychological Institute, University of Innsbruck, Austria
1948 Author, Zapiski bezbozhnika
1948-1965 Professor, Universidad Nacional de La Plata, Argentina
1949 Author, Otets Aleksandr
1965 Author, Kul'tura dushi i kul'tura dukha Died, Argentina
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of the literary works of Boris Nikolaevich Kompaneiskii, a scientist specializing in human perception of color and light. He was also known to have used the pseudonym N. Kovalenskii.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Physiology.; Russian literature.; Russians--Argentina.; Russia (Federation).; Soviet Union.; Argentina.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1958-1973. (Box 1)
  Curriculum vitae and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Writings, 1921-1952. (Box 1)
  Plays, sketches, short stories, and a novel, arranged chronologically by title
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1958-1973 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitae. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes associated correspondence relating to the transfer of Kompaneiskii's writings to the Museum of Russian Culture by his widow, Lydia, 1973
  - Miscellany. (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes partial inventory
- WRITINGS, 1921-1952
  - "Iskuplenie," n.d. (Folder 1: 3)
    Typescript
  - "Iskusstvennyi bog," n.d. (Folder 1: 4)
  - "Piat' chudes mira," n.d.
    - Russian (Folder 1: 5)
    - English (entitled "The Five Miracles of the World") (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - "Practical Application of Dr. Kompaneysky's Research Works in Fine Arts," n.d. (Folder 1: 7)
  - "Practical Application of Dr. Kompaneysky's Work for Military Defence," n.d. (Folder 1: 8)
  - "Prizraki," n.d. (Folder 1: 9)
  - "Sozviezdie Khrista," n.d. (Folder 1: 10)
    Printed copy
  - "Sviatoi muchenik Uar," n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
  - "Volshebnyi obruch," n.d. (Folder 1: 12)
  - "Liubov' rebenka," 1921. (Folder 1: 13)
  - "Iskushenie," 1921 March 20. (Folder 1: 14)
  - "Glaza Meri," 1923 October 23. (Folder 1: 15)
  - "Zhivye maski," 1923 November 25. (Folder 1: 16)
  - "Inzhener," 1925 July 12. (Folder 1: 17)
  - "Satana," 1931. (Folder 1: 18)
  - "Ee dnevnik," 1932 August 12. (Folder 1: 19)
  - "Oktologiia: Misteriia zemli," 1932 August 20. (Folder 1: 20)
  - "Sv. Pelageia," 1933 September 20. (Folder 1: 21)
  - "Gala," 1935 August 22. (Folder 1: 22)
  - "Sv. Matrona," 1935 November 7. (Folder 1: 23)
  - "Tret'e izmerenie," translation into Russian of a work by Edward Iversen, 1936 August 5. (Folder 1: 24)
  - "Vechnost'," 1937 November 9. (Folder 1: 25)
  - "Puteshestvie po zvezdnym miram," 1945 May 28. (Folder 1: 26)
  - Zapiski bezbozhnika, 1948. (Folder 1: 27)
  - Otets Aleksandr, 1949. (Folder 1: 28)
  - "New Principles in the Color Science," English abstract of "Nuevos Principios de la Ciencia del Color," Acta Argentina de Fisiologiia y Fisiopatologia, 1952. (Folder 1: 29)